Brighton, Boston, Mass. Faneuil Congregational Church records, 1884-1984.
Congregational Library & Archives
Brighton, Boston, Mass. Faneuil Congregational Church records, 1884-1984.
RG0025
Congregational Library & Archives
2.99 Cubic Feet
(2 cartons, 2 boxes)
The Faneuil Congregational Church was organized in the Brighton area of Boston, MA from 1903 to 1976. It grew out of the Faneuil Sunday School and built its own church building in 1913. The church closed in 1975 and was officially dissolved in 1976 due to the lack of membership. The collection contains records about the administration and history of Faneuil church and some of the organizations within it. The collection includes correspondence, meeting minutes, constitution and bylaws, annual reports, church registers, membership lists, baptismal records, account ledgers, treasurer's reports, service programs, materials relating to the 50th anniversary of the church, sermons (1937) of minister Aaron N. Meckel, photographs, newspaper clippings, a gavel and publications from or about the church.
Faneuil Congregational Church (Brighton, Boston, Mass.)
Meckel, Aaron N. (Aaron Nathaniel), 1904-
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Originally deposited 24 October 1975 with the Congregational Christian Historical Society, Boston, Mass. by Roy B. Stewart, clerk, and Rev. Harry W. Mason Jr, on behalf of the church. Converted to Gift 3 December 1985 by Metropolitan Boston Association of the Massachusetts Conference of the United Church of Christ.
Historical Note
The Faneuil Congregational Church was located in the Brighton area of Boston, Mass and existed from 1903 to 1976. The church grew from the Faneuil Sunday School which began in 1877 to serve the children of the Faneuil area so that they did not have to travel to Brighton Congregational Church. The Sunday school began classes at the home of James W. Harvey on Newton Street before moving to a rented room in a store on Brooks Street. In 1900, Faneuil Chapel was built for the school and was dedicated in November of that year. The school continued to operate out of the chapel until 1914 when the new church building was completed, and the chapel was sold to the City of Boston to be used as a public library. In 1941, Faneuil Church repurchased the chapel and moved the school back to that location until the school's closure in 1972 due to a lack of students.
In 1903, the community of Faneuil came together to create their own church separate from Brighton Congregational Church and incorporated the Faneuil Congregational Church of Boston in January 1903. The first service of the church was held at Faneuil Chapel on February 4, 1903. In May 1903, the first permanent pastor, Rev. Andrew H. Mulnix, began serving the church and remained pastor until his resignation in December 1935. In January 1911, the mortgage for the Faneuil Chapel was paid and a service was held to commemorate the burning of the mortgage. The church began plans for a new building after 1911 and construction was completed in December 1913. The mortgage for the new building was paid and burned in January 1924. The church bought and installed a new organ in October 1925 and a new chancel window in November 1930.
The church celebrated its 25th anniversary in February 1928. In 1935, Rev. Mulnix resigned and was replaced in May 1936 by Rev. Aaron N. Meckel who served the church until March 1941. In 1953, Faneuil Church celebrated its 50th anniversary with a special service and other events. In 1969, Rev. Harry W. Mason Jr began serving the church and remained as pastor until its closure. In the 1970s as the membership and budget declined, the church began plans to close. The last service was held on June 29, 1975 and the final annual meeting for the dissolution of Faneuil Congregational Church corporation was held in January 1976 at Brighton Center Church where many members had moved. The materials owned by the church were returned to the original donor, given to the Brighton Historical Society, thrown away, or entrusted to the United Church of Christ. The church building was sold to the Central New England District of the United Pentecostal Church in 1975, while the parish house had been sold previously to Edward P. Long in 1963. Any remaining funds were separated among various charities or given to the Massachusetts Conference of the UCC.
The Faneuil church was home to multiple organizations throughout its lifetime. The Women's Association began in November 1901 and remained heavily involved in the church operation until its dissolution in 1976. The Pilgrim League began in 1924 for the business women and young mothers of the church and merged with the Women's Association in 1932. The Men's club began in or before 1926 and existed until 1975 when the church closed.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains records for the Faneuil Congregational Church for its entire lifetime of 1903-1976, with some earlier records from the Faneuil Sunday School and some later financial records. The collection includes volumes of meeting minutes, treasurer's account books, receipt ledger books, and church registers. It also includes folders of correspondence, annual reports, treasury reports, meeting minutes, service programs, publications, member lists, baptismal records, bylaws and constitutions, legal precedings, financial records, newspaper clippings, member dismission forms, photographs, minister sermons, and histories. The collection also includes a film reel of the church's 50th anniversary, a gavel, and a box of member contact cards. The records are from or about the church itself, its members, or the organizations within it.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series, one of which has four sub-series. The series and the records within them are arranged chronologically by start date.
Series 1: History of Faneuil congregational church, 1884-1969
Series 2: Organization records, 1901-1975
Subseries 1: Women's association, 1901-1975
Subseries 2: Missionary auxiliary group, 1914-1932
Subseries 3: Pilgrim league, 1924-1932
Subseries 4: Faneuil men's club, 1927-1975
Series 3: Administrative records, 1903-1975
Series 4: Member records, 1903-1976
Series 5: Financial records, 1934-1984
Baptismal records.; Church anniversaries.; Church closures; Church finance.; Church management.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Faneuil Congregational Church (Brighton, Boston, Mass.); Brighton (Boston, Mass.) -- Church history.
- History of Faneuil congregational church, 1884 1969; 1884-1969; 6 Folders; 1 Reels; 1 Object
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records relating to the history of Faneuil Congregational Church from the start of the Faneuil Sunday School to the close of the church. It includes photographs, correspondence, publications, service programs, sermons, newspaper clippings, member lists, reports, a film reel for the church's 50th anniversary, and a gavel.
  - Photographs, 1880 1953; circa 1880-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Programs, publications, and mailings, 1884 1960; 1884-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Records of 50th anniversary, 1900 1954; 1900-1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Gavel, 1903 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1913 1951; 1913-1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence on changing pastors, 1935 1969; 1935-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Aaron N. Meckel's sermons, 1937 1939; 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Film of 50th anniversary, 1953 (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Organization records, 1901 1975; 1901-1975; 9 Volumes; 5 Folders
  This series contains records from or about various organizations within Faneuil Congregational Church including the Women's Association, the Pilgrim League, the Men's Club, and the Missionary Auxilary Group. The majority of the records are for the Women's Association. The series includes nine volumes of treasurer's account books and meeting minutes; and five folders of annual reports, meeting minutes, member lists, bylaws, and correspondence for the organizations.
  - Women's association, 1901 1975; 1901-1975; 7 Volumes; 3 Folders
    This sub-series contains records for the Women's Association of Faneuil Congregational Church. It includes seven volumes of treasurer's account books and meeting minutes; and three folders of meeting minutes, annual reports, and bylaws for the association.
    - Treasurer's account book, 1901 1908; 1901-1908 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - Record book, 1901 1909; 1901-1909 (Box 1, Volume 4)
      Related Materials
      Loose papers were removed and placed in the folder labeled Papers from record book, 1901-1909, 1901.
    - Papers from record book, 1901-1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      The papers were removed from the volume labeled Record book, 1901-1909.
    - Annual reports, 1901 1953; 1901-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Treasurer's account book, 1908 1913; 1908-1913 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    - Treasurer's account book, 1914 1940; 1914-1940 (Box 1, Volume 6)
    - Meeting minutes, 1922 1938; 1922-1938 (Box 2, Volume 5)
    - Meeting minutes, 1938 1950; 1938-1950 (Box 2, Volume 6)
    - Meeting minutes, 1949 1962; 1949-1962 (Box 2, Volume 7)
    - Meeting minutes, 1963 1975; 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Missionary auxiliary group, 1914 1932; 1914-1932; 1 Volume
    This series contains records for the Missionary Auxilary Group at Faneuil Congregational Church. It includes one volume of a treasurer's account book.
    - Treasurer's book, 1914 1932; 1914-1932 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Pilgrim league, 1924 1932; 1924-1932; 1 Volume; 1 Folder
    This series contains records for the Pilgim League at Faneuil Congregational Church. It includes one volume of meeting minutes and bylaws; and one folder of annual reports for the organization. The Pilgrim League merged into the Women's Association of Faneuil Congregational Church in 1932.
    - Record book, 1924 1925; 1924-1925 (Box 1, Volume 7)
    - Annual reports, 1924 1932; 1924-1932 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Faneuil men's club, 1927 1975; 1927-1975; 1 Folder
    This sub-series contains records for the Men's Club of Faneuil Congregational Church. It includes one folder of meeting minutes, member lists, correspondence, and bylaws for the organization.
    - Men's club records, 1927 1975; 1927-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Administrative records, 1903 1975; 1903-1975; 4 Volumes; 4 Folders
  The administrative records were created throughout the lifetime of Faneuil church from 1903-1975. The records include four volumes of meeting minutes with some related papers inserted, and four folders with annual reports, correspondence, meeting minutes, publications, and church laws all relating to the running and administration of Faneuil Church.
  - Record book no 1, 1903 1914; 1903-1914 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Laws of government, 1907 1967; 1907-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Record book no 2, 1914 1931; 1914-1931 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Record book no 3, 1931 1935; 1931-1935 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Record book no 4, 1935 1949; 1935-1949 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Annual reports, 1941 1975; 1941-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Distribution and sale of church property, 1972 1975; 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Records for dissolution of Faneuil church, 1974 1975; 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Member records, 1903 1976; 1903-1976; 2 Volumes; 6 Folders; 1 Box
  This series includes vital statistics for the members of Faneuil Congregational Church. It incldudes two volumes of church registers; three folders of correspondence, mailing lists, officer lists, member lists, and letters of dismission forms; three folders of information cards for members and baptisms; and one box of member contact cards.
  - Member card list, undated (Box 4)
  - Church register, 1903 1976; 1903-1976 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Membership files, 1909 1976; 1909-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Church register, 1914 1976; 1914-1976 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Member lists, 1935 1939; 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Baptismal records, M-Z, 1937 1976; 1937-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baptismal records, A-L, 1937 1976; 1937-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters of dismission, 1957 1976; 1957-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mailing lists, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial records, 1934 1984; 1934-1984; 4 Folders; 3 Volumes
  The series contains financial records for Faneuil Church from 1934 to 1984. It includes three volumes of reciept or account ledgers for the church, and four folders with correspondence, treasurer's reports, legal precedings, and newspaper clippings. Due to delays in court relating to an estate that included a bequest to Faneuil Congregational Church, the financial records continue past the closure of the church.
  - Receipt and disbursement ledger, 1934 1969; 1934-1969 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Account ledger, 1948 1964; 1948-1964 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Bequests to Faneuil Congregational Church, 1948 1984; 1948-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1950 1976; 1950-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence for parish house mortgage, 1963 1968; 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Account ledger, 1965 1975; 1965-1975 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Land damage claim, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)